9-11. I mean, we did of course see the destruction of Al Qaeda, we saw the killing of Osama bin
Laden, we saw the US pull out of Afghanistan, but in your mind is what we are seeing now
in the Middle East some way of a continuation of that war on terror or is it something
else? Is it something new?
Well, I think it is partly a continuation of it. Yeah. We saw, as you say, the defeat of Al
Qaeda, but then of course we had Al Qaeda in Iraq, which kind of grew out of it. There was
a claim of victory against Al Qaeda in Iraq. But then we had ISIS, which which grew
to a large extent out of Al Qaeda in Iraq. So you have this sort of serial declaration
of victories. And then people can relax for a little bit. But then something else happens.
And a lot of times these threats are feeding into each other. There's a continuity
between these organizations. I think, you know, the destruction of Gaza, you know,
that is in a way a very distinct problem. But it was an action that was presented by
Israel within the framework of a war on terror. In Sri Lanka, where I was in 2009,
you know, the government wreaked horrible destruction on the Tamil population in the
name of an international war on terror. And it was actually difficult for Britain or
the United States to criticize that. You know, when they themselves were detaining
people indefinitely, they themselves had the language of the war on terror. And we need
to be ruthless. We need to suspend liberty to a certain extent in the interest of
security.
Specifically on the language used around the war on terror, I guess a very seismic
symbolic shift at least came with the rebranding of the Secretary of Defense to
the Secretary of War, the Defense Department to the War Department. Because I mean,
that signaled almost a kind of move away from more of a reactive war on terror to a US
administration that sought to project power to pursue a peace through strength, I think
is the words used by by Pete Hegseth. So do you see that as a rebranding of what's
gone before? Or is that really a defining departure from what we've seen in the
past?
I think it's a great question. I think it is partly rebranding. But it's partly
an indication that violence and the assertion of America's right in particular
to do what it's like to do what it likes has become sort of incredibly
shameless under Trump. And Trump is somebody really who has systematically
rejected shame and indeed made a lot of political capital, in my opinion, out
of offering people a kind of vicarious shamelessness through his abuses and
through his spectacular demonstrations of freedom, as I say, freedom for for
himself. So I think, you know, there are some significant differences. For
example, George W. Bush and Tony Blair, you know, they did make some efforts to
try to create some sense of international legitimacy for what they
wanted to do in Iraq, and to try and get the UN on board to a certain extent.
We're not seeing that now with Trump and Netanyahu. We're just seeing a kind of
go it alone spirit, which I think is incredibly dangerous and incredibly
destructive. So I do think there's a shamelessness about what's going on.
And that thing you mentioned about relabeling as a department of war,
you know, Trump would say, well, this is, you know, this is honesty. You know,
he projects this image of honesty. I'm not a hypocrite. The liberals are
hypocrites. I tell you the truth as it is. And he's made some considerable
political capital out of that, in my opinion. But it's also a very frightening
turn.
David, talking about political capital, we've talked about the big powers.
I'd like to talk about the small powers, if I may, because I wonder if the
rise of non-state actors, Hezbollah in Lebanon, the Houthis in Yemen,
whether they fit into this into this frame as well, because I want to know if
they are motivated by the same impulses that perhaps Iran or the United
States may be for their own ends. I mean, how does your approach to
this work when war is being waged by smaller paramilitary networks? Okay,
some see Hezbollah as being almost a kind of mini-franchise of Iran in the same
way that you would view the branch of a bank internationally. But is that a
wrong way of looking at this?
Well, I think a lot of these non-state actors, you know, they do very often
have state backers, you know, and we've seen it with Hezbollah. We've
seen it with the rapid support forces and the UAE in Sudan. So we can't sort
of regard them simply as non-state actors. I think that, you know, in the case
of Hezbollah in Lebanon, you know, there has been quite a strong effort
from the Lebanese government to weaken Hezbollah. And that's something
that can potentially, I think, bear a lot of fruit. And then when Israel comes
in and starts bombing Lebanon and displacing, you know, as I understand
it, a million people, you know, this can easily set things back. So the
states tend to sort of weigh in on these struggles, these local
struggles, often in extremely counterproductive ways. I think Sudan, you
know, is an interesting case of a government that, you know, going back
to the 1980s, tried to mobilize militias, mobilize his own militias for the
purposes of counterinsurgency. But then the government, in a way, lost
control of the violence because the militias were economically motivated to
a large extent. They spread rebellion to new areas. And on the whole, they
refused to disband after particular military campaigns. And they became, as
were, a political factor in their own right. And we know that the RSF, you
know, is a successor to the Janjaweed militias that created the Darfur
genocide. And it's been a huge factor in Sudan politics ever since, you
know, basically extorting the government, using gold in particular to
build up its strength, and eventually turning against the army with the
result of this horrific civil war that we have at the moment. So
militias don't always obey what their puppet masters tell them to do. And
that can be very destructive in itself.
David, can a conflict like the Iran-Israel rivalry ever truly end, taking
in everything you've discussed? Or does that system, does that system
simply evolve into new forms of hybrid warfare, or to protect
essentially underlying profit margins and existing power structures?
Well, I think conflicts can come to an end. I think a lot of people
thought that the Cold War would never end, because partly of the vested
interests enfold. But it did actually surprise us by ending. Of
course, people who were making the argument that it will never end
will now point to various aspects of a revival of the Cold War, you
know, in terms of Russia, and even China, and so on. So I do
think sometimes that violence is a little bit like energy, you know, in
the sense that it can change from one form to another. But it very
rarely disappears entirely. In practice, I think, you know, one of
the things you can do is to make peace more profitable and more
attractive for various warring parties than war itself, you
know, can offer them a stake in a political settlement in a
peace process, you can buy them off if you like. One of the
problems with that, of course, is that you are you tend to
entrench corruption and indeed violence within the peace
settlement that you're actually creating or offering.
David, in a fragmented global economy, I mean, how does the
political conflict of those big powers, the political conflict
that we are seeing play out in the Middle East? I mean, how does
that affect the global south? How does that affect nations that
are watching from the sidelines or simultaneously protecting the
big powers and Washington DC in Beijing or Moscow, for instance?
I think there are a lot of economic impacts as well. You
know, for example, the World Food Programme now is talking
about perhaps 45 million people facing severe food shortages and
starvation as a result of the war that's currently going on
with Iran and Israel and the United States. So, you know, we
know that oil prices are going up. We know that fertilizer
prices have been drastically affected. This affects food
production and it affects people's food security. And I think,
you know, if we go back in history just a little bit to, for
example, 2011, you know, you had a huge increase in global food
prices for various reasons. And that fed rather directly into
famine in places like Yemen and Somalia. And it also fed
into the so-called Arab Spring and the Civil War in Syria,
for example. So these kind of knock-on effects, you know,
that they're not always predictable, but I think you can predict
that many of them are going to be extremely bad and the people
that are going to suffer are going to be, you know, very far
from from Washington or Jerusalem. David King, thank you
for talking to Al Jazeera.
Yeah, pleasure to talk to you.
As the war on Iran escalates, Al Jazeera correspondence
are on the ground. Donald Trump says he intends to speak to the
Iranians in the next couple of days, but added he has no idea
who will be on the other end of the call. Well, most of the
people we had in mind are dead. A lot of signs, people saying
that the U.S. should not be attacking Iran, calling on
Congress to act. Members of Congress are away from Washington
this weekend. There needs to be the proof of an imminent
threat to American interest. This was our last best
chance to strike. The U.S. Senate has decided they're
not going to step in and stop this ever expanding war.
Stay with Al Jazeera for the latest developments.
Tehran, a city where centuries of history rise from its
histories and monuments, now coming under assault. At the
heart of the city stands Kolesan Palace, more than four
centuries old, a witness to coronations and major
political decisions, but now damaged by American and
Israeli airstrikes. International organizations
like UNESCO warn about the impact of these attacks on our
collective heritage. They are UNESCO World Heritage
sites, priceless treasures that belong to all of humanity.
Many now fear that centuries of history could become
another casualty of war. Hello, this is Al Jazeera live
from Doha with our continuing coverage of the war
between the U.S., Israel and Iran. I'm Riley Carlson.
Here's what's coming up. Donald Trump sets a Tuesday
deadline for Iran to reopen the Strait of Hormuz or the U.S.
will bomb its power plants, bridges and quote, unleash hell.
We are determined to defend Iran's foreign ministry
dismisses the U.S. president's warning and vows a swift
retaliation to any U.S. attacks. That is airstrike
slam into Tehran province. At least 23 people have been
killed, including six children. At least five people
have been killed in an Israeli strike on Lebanon's
capital. We're live in Beirut's southern suburb and
more Iranian attacks target Israeli cities. Two bodies
have been recovered from the rubble of a destroyed
apartment building in Haifa. U.S. president Donald
Trump has renewed threats to destroy Iranian power
plants and bridges if it doesn't reopen the
Strait of Hormuz. He shared what appears to be
a deadline on social media Tuesday, 8 p.m. Eastern
time. Earlier, Trump posted an expletive laden threat
to his true social account. It promised that Iranians
would be quote living in hell if the Strait isn't
reopened. Tehran has emphasized that it will
retaliate if struck. Foreign ministry spokesman
Ismail Bagai says any U.S. related location in the
Middle East would be a target. Our armed forces
have made it clear that in case Iran's
infrastructure is attacked, we would react in
kind. Our armed forces would target any similar
infrastructure that is owned or in any way or
manner related to the United States or
contributes to their act of aggression against
Iran. We will be live from Tehran in just a
moment, but first, Al Jazeera's Mike Hanna
has more on the president's comments from
Washington, D.C.
The unusual use of an expletive by a national
leader, perhaps a symbol of President Trump's
frustration with the Iranian government and
their refusal to concede to the demands that he
is making. That reference as well was to the
Strait of Hormuz, which in recent days,
President Trump had insisted he did not care
about saying the U.S. did not need the oil
passing through the Strait and it was up to
the countries who are reliant on that oil to
deal with the situation. But now the demand
about opening the Strait of Hormuz appears
front and center of the president's new
demands of the Iranian government.
President Trump threatening to, and I use
his words, blowing everything and taking
the oil if Iran does not meet his new
deadline, which has now been set at 8 p.m.
Eastern time on Tuesday evening. He says
in an earlier media post that a power plant
day and bridge day all wrapped up on
Tuesday. But on the other hand, in addition
to these threats, President Trump is sending
signals that there's some kind of negotiation
process underway. He's indicated that his
close confidants, Jared Kushner and Stephen
Whitcoff, are in consultation with either
the Iranian government and identified figures
or some form of intermediary. And speaking
to US news outlets, President Trump says
that he is optimistic that there can be an
agreement very soon. He says the agreement
could come within a matter of days rather
than a matter of weeks. So you've got this
dichotomous approach from the president on
the one hand threatening obliteration to
civilian targets within Iran, which some
observers would contend to be a war crime.
But on the other hand, what he is saying
is, yes, we are talking, the talks are going
well, and they could come to fruition
before that new deadline I set, which is
8 p.m. Eastern time on Tuesday.
Mike Hanna, Al Jazeera, Washington.
The speaker of Iran's parliament has also
responded to Trump. In a social media
post, Mohamed Begur Ghalibov wrote,
Your reckless moves are dragging the United
States into a living hell for every
single family. And our whole region is
going to burn because you insist on
following Netanyahu's commands, make no
mistake, you won't gain anything through
war crimes. Meanwhile, overnight and
early morning, U.S. Israeli attacks on
Iran have killed at least 34 people.
Strikes across Tehran province have left
at least 23 people dead, including half
a dozen children. The capital itself has
also been hit. A separate attack on a
residential area in the city of Qom,
south of Tehran, killed five people.
And in southern Iran, a strike on the
city of Bandar Leng has killed another
six. Let's bring in Tohira Sadina, who
joins us live from Tehran.
Tohe, the Israeli military, says the
waves of strikes against government
infrastructure in Tehran was completed
just a short time ago. What more can
you tell us about the attacks that
took place overnight and into this
morning?
Well, actually, Tehran had another
night of heavy bombardment last night
in the eastern southern, as well as
the western parts of the capital, but
the most notable one, I think, happened
in the Sharif University of Technology,
the campus at which was targeted,
leaving an unprecedentedly
huge amount of damage to this building
and the other buildings in the areas
near the campus. And of course, we
know that a gas facility was also
targeted around the area.
And we know that it is four major
university that has been targeted
over the past few weeks, showing the
extended scope of the Israeli
and American strikes now targeting
more infrastructural areas, including
universities, hospitals, schools, oil
related and still related
infrastructure, all putting a huge
amount of pressure on the economy of
the country. But beyond the capital,
we know that in other cities, we
had the continued campaign of
the air strikes by the Americans
and Israelis in the cities of Karaj, Tehran,
Shiraz, Isfahan and Boushehr.
We've got the reports and footages
coming about, the severe damages
to the areas as a result of these
attacks in Bandar-e-Lingas.
You mentioned six people in Wom five
people and in the Baharistan,
a small city located in the southern
areas of the capital.
At least 13 people, according to
the local authorities, have been killed,
among which, excuse me, six
were children. We're dealing with these
air strikes continuing and
impacting the very infrastructure of
the country following the recent
threats by the U.S. President Donald Trump.
Yeah, and, Toheed, on those threats
from the U.S. president, what else is
Iran saying about either those
threats or the prospect of any change
to the situation in the Strait of
Hormuz?
Yes, indeed. We're dealing with a
sort of high-stakes situation, but
according to what we hear from the
Iranian side, first, they're not that
much unfamiliar with this threatening
language. It's like dancing with the
same old tune for them. Since the very
beginning of this war, they're facing
threats, but this is not just
limited to this war, but earlier also
they had this language experienced,
but also we know that they're taking
it quite seriously, seeing as I told
you, the extended nature of the
scope of the attacks over the past one
or two weeks, I would say, and the
message furthermore that is coming from
Tehran is that of defiance, the
resilience and deterrence, and, of
course, retaliation. They are saying
that in case of more attacks on the
infrastructure of the country, there is
going to be a tit for tat strategy
targeting the U.S. assets across the
region or any infrastructure in which
the United States has got a share or
in a sense associated with, and of
course, the Israeli territories, but
speaking of the strait of Hormuz, again
we are hearing a lot of statements from
the Iranian side. The gist of the
matter is that the country is trying
to use it as a leverage point in this
already actually intricate situation,
seeing the geostrategically
significant role of this chalk point,
and they're also trying to implement
plans to impose tariffs for the
ships which are planning to pass
through and last but not least, they
are saying that it's not open, it's not
close, it's open to everyone, it's close
to our adversaries. All right, Toheed
Asadi reporting live for us from Tehran.
Toheed, thanks. The threat of
escalation in Iran puts the Gulf
region squarely in the crossfire.
The sites Iran is threatening to hit
back at are almost entirely located in
GCC countries, which are already coping
with daily attacks. Kuwait says it
has been hit by a series of drone
attacks. Authorities report that two
major power and desalination plans
were targeted. One of those facilities
is in Al-Zor, nearly 90 kilometers
south of Kuwait City. Another attack
hit the finance ministry complex.
That building is in central Kuwait
city. In Bahrain, Iran targeted an
oil facility sparking several fires.
Emergency response teams said the
blaze has been fully extinguished.
Over the past few weeks, Minama has
come under repeated Iranian missile
and drone attacks. Malik Trena is live
with us now from Kuwait City. Malik,
how concerned are Gulf countries
about the U.S. president's threats
of escalation here? Extremely
concerned, to say the least, Riley.
I mean, you know, the secretary
general of the GCC, Jassamid
Abdaoui, earlier this week, said
that 85 percent of the
retaliation attacks coming from Iran
have targeted the Gulf, you know,
more than 6,000 now ballistic
missiles and drones have targeted
this entire region. So people become
extremely concerned, you know,
just in the last 30 to 40 minutes or
so. We heard about authorities
responding to an incident in Abu
Dhabi and the industrial city of
Abu Dhabi, where debris from a
interception injured one person.
In the last couple of hours, we've
seen alarms raised here in Kuwait
and also, more so, and a few
others in the UAE.
You know, yesterday was a really
devastating day for people here
in Kuwait. You know, we had two
water and power, water desalination
plants targeted the Azur plant
that you mentioned earlier. It's
one of the biggest in the Middle
East. So the Iranians have proven
that they can't target and
hit civil
civilian infrastructure here in the
Gulf. So that's extremely worrying.
You know, whenever President Trump
escalates, Iran retaliates.
And so, you know, people who what
I've seen in the last couple of
days, Riley is
authorities here in Kuwait have
been putting power generate huge
power generators next to
distribution, electricity
distribution centers that just goes
to show you that authorities here
are, you know, making
contingency plans for if this war
escalates. You know, I think the
call has been to de-escalate the
situation and try to bring this
war to an end. Nobody here
across the region wants to see
things increase, increase, you
know, increase and escalate.
They certainly do not. Malik
Trayna live for us in Kuwait
City. Malik, thank you.
In Lebanon, the Israeli army has
carried out new strikes on Beirut's
southern suburb in a densely
populated residential area.
The death toll has now risen to
at least five, including three
Sudanese nationals.
52 others were injured in those
strikes.
Three more people were killed
in an air strike in the hills
of Ainsade.
Israel says its continuing
attacks on Hezbollah military
infrastructure, more than a
million people have been
forcibly displaced across the
country.
They hit a completely
civilian area.
It's mostly migrants here,
Sudanese people.
People were at home and they
struck them.
Are those military objectives?
Where is the UN?
No one says anything.
Aren't they human too?
They're killing children and
women.
The whole world has to speak
up.
It has to see and say
something.
Have we become nothing but
numbers, a people of numbers?
How is that possible?
We are devastated.
Our morale is low.
When you see your friends and
neighbors in pieces on the
ground and blood everywhere and
the house destroyed, our
house was destroyed.
Where are we going to sleep?
Where do we go?
Zena Hodder joins us live now
from Beirut and Zena.
You can hear there in what
these people are saying,
how concerning it is for them
that the civilian death toll
in Lebanon continues to
climb ever higher.
What more can you tell us?
Well, civilians are
increasingly being caught
in this conflict.
1,461 people have been
killed in this conflict,
which has now entered its
sixth week with more than
4,000 people injured.
Yesterday, in an Israeli
strike in Znech, which is
on the fringe of the Beirut
Southern suburbs, it was
a densely populated area.
The apparent target was a
Hezbollah military commander,
but three Sudanese
nationals were killed,
along with a 15-year-old
child.
So even though the Israeli
military may call these
targeted strikes, pinpoint
strikes, when they go
after a certain individual
member of Hezbollah, at time
civilians are killed.
There was another incident
in Ain Saadi, that's north
of Beirut, where three
civilians were killed.
This is an area outside
Hezbollah's influence,
a predominantly Christian
neighborhood.
And those who were killed
are really not part of
this conflict, this ongoing
conflict, and it's raising
and heightening tensions
in those regions
because people there
are blaming Hezbollah
and Hezbollah supporters
for seeking shelter
in those areas.
And then you have strikes
in the south of the country,
for example, in the village
of Toul, in Nabatiyeh,
where a father and a mother
were killed.
And their 15-year-old
and nine-year-old child
were wounded.
And there have been
several instances where
whole families are killed
in a single strike.
So the civilian death toll
is rising according
to the statistics
that are being provided
by the Lebanese Health
Ministry, because they don't
really distinguish
between combatants and civilians.
But among the women,
children, and the paramedics
who have been killed,
we are talking about
roughly 25 percent
of the casualty toll.
All right, Zayna.
And while we have you,
let's talk about where Israel
is in terms of its ground
invasion in southern Lebanon.
What are they saying
right now about it?
Well, the Israeli military
is operating in southern Lebanon.
But in the past 24, 48 hours,
they haven't made any
significant military gains
on the ground.
Yes, they have territorial control
of some areas along that border.
But territorial control
does not mean operational control
because Hezbollah continues
to fight back.
It is putting up resistance.
And then we heard from
the Israeli Chief of Staff
on Sunday, where he said,
yes, Israel's ultimate goal
is to disarm Hezbollah.
But the goal of the current campaign
is about advancing this goal.
He does not use the word achieve.
He uses the word advance.
And he also calls on the political leadership
to play a part.
So this is the Israeli army saying
that even though they reach up
until the Letani River,
the stated goal of this invasion,
it's not going to achieve Hezbollah's disarmament.
The Israeli military knows very well
that Hezbollah's strategic infrastructure
and strategic weapons